Okay, today's daf is דף ח Daf Ches Kiddushin 8, and this
is Rabbi Linzer today. And although yesterday's daf we ended a few
lines into ח עמוד א, Ches Amud Aleph, I want us to
take us from the top because to really frame the issue and
the debate here between רבה Rabba and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So
to review, the גמרא Gemara had discussed a case about somebody who
married a woman or attempted to do קידושין Kiddushin with a woman
and gave her some silk, and the question was whether the silk
needed to be assessed, did it צריכי שומא, tzrichi shuma, before it
was given to the woman for the קידושין Kiddushin to be good.
And רבה Rabba said it did not and רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said it did. And the גמרא Gemara has two versions of the
debate. According to version number one, the case was that the man
asserted a certain value of it. He said it's worth fifty dollars,
and it turns out it was worth fifty dollars, but it had
not been determined that that was the case before it was given
to the woman. So רבה Rabba said it was what he said
it was and she's married. רב יוסף Rav Yosef said no, even
though it turned out that way, if you don't have an expert
assess it, a layperson cannot really easily assess the value of that,
and she's not so certain. And it's funny, I mean, she did
agree to accept it, but since he says that we can't assume
that she was really certain and confident of its value, that is
a problem in terms of sufficient דעת da'as for קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay,
that's one case, when a value has been claimed and it's not
clear at the moment whether it's worth that value. The second version
of the debate is even more interesting, and that is where he
says, doesn't claim any value, I'm marrying you with whatever it's worth,
I don't know what it's worth, I mean, it's certainly worth a
פרוטה, perutah, but I'm not claiming anything about its value. And so
that means, so of course now we certainly understand רבה, Rabba, why
does it have to be assessed? But רב יוסף Rav Yosef said,
no, in this case it does have to be assessed where no
value is given to it. And let's see why, and we'll pick
up at the bottom of ז עמוד ב. Zayin Amud Beis. איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, this is the last four words of the second
to last line, בכולהו נמי פליגי, b'chulehu nami pligi, even if it
he's saying whatever it's worth, they debate. רב יוסף אמר שוה כסף
הרי הוא ככסף. Rav Yosef amar shaveh kessef harei hu k'kessef. Yes,
there is a principle that things of monetary value is like money,
but the point is, like money, that it has to function as
money. Now we know that, how do we know this principle that
a woman is married with כסף, kessef, with money? Either from the
case of the man selling his daughter for an אמה עבריה amah
Ivriyah בכסף, b'kessef, or by the case of אברהם Avraham and שדה
עפרון, Sadeh Ephron, you know, where he gives him, you know, it
says עובר לסוחר, oveir lasocher, ארבע מאות שקל כסף. arba meios shekel
kessef. So in those cases, okay, that was real money, actually it's
a drasha, some people question whether it was minted money by אברהם
Avraham or it was just the weight of silver, but it was
still functioning very much, even if it was
weighted silver, it was functioning as money. Now even though we have
a principle that we learn out, and there's a question how do
we learn it out, where do we learn it out from, but
in many, many cases שוה כסף shaveh kessef is like כסף. kessef.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef comes and makes an important point, and he
says that does not mean that the הלכה halacha is that you
can marry somebody with something of value. The הלכה halacha still is
that a woman needs to be married with money, but things of
value can serve as if they were money. So he
says מה כסף דקייץ, ma kessef d'katitz, ח עמוד א Ches Amud
Aleph now, אף שוה כסף נמי דקייץ. af shaveh kessef nami d'katitz.
The same way money has a fixed value, you know, that's the
whole idea of money, you know, you know exactly one dollar, two
dollars, twenty-three dollars and seventy-two cents.
So even when something is שוה כסף, shaveh kessef, it has to
be have a fixed value. And if something, you know, you have
no, you know, it's ambiguous or, you know, indeterminate, not yet determined
what its value is—I mean, I see this silk, it could be
worth anywhere from ten dollars to a hundred dollars, I have no
idea—so then it doesn't function as money. Certainly it's an object of
value, but it can't function as money without a fixed set value
to it. So therefore he says it needs to be assessed beforehand,
צריכי שומא. tzrichi shuma. So that is a, once you think about
it in those terms, it's a really a compelling position if it
has to function as כסף kessef and not fundamentally serve as שוה
כסף. shaveh kessef. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, מנא ליה, minalia, where do I get this idea from?
דתניא, detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, מכסף מקנתו, mikessef miknaso, this is said about an
עבד עברי eved Ivri that he has to be, he's going to
be redeemed from the money of his purchase. So this teaches us
both about, you know, how he is purchased and how he is
redeemed, it's from כסף. kessef. בכסף הוא נפדה ואינו נפדה בתבואה וכלים.
b'kessef hu nifdeh v'eino nifdeh b'tevuah v'keilim. So the ברייתא braisa teaches
that it only can be money and not with grain, not with
food, and not with vessels. Now האי תבואה וכלים היכי דמי, hai
tevuah v'keilim heichi dami, now that sounds like it might be a
standard, a basic rejection of the idea of שוה כסף shaveh kessef
in this case. But we're not going to say that. So let's
figure this out. What does it mean that it can't be with
grain and with vessels? אילימא דלא מקנו בהו כלל, ilima delo maknu
behu klal, if it's that they can't work at all, you know,
you can't purchase him with it, it has to be money
literally. ישיב גאולתו, yashiv geulato, you shall return, restore, you know, his
redemption, אמר רחמנא, amar rachmana, so the fact that it's very generic
and it doesn't mention כסף, kesef, לרבות שווה כסף ככסף. lerabot shaveh
kesef kekesef. That teaches us and in every case, you know, you
need to learn this principle the beginning of בבא קמא Bava Kamma
has to learn it applying across many, many, many cases. How do
you know שווה כסף shaveh kesef is like כסף? kesef? So here
this teaches us that שווה כסף shaveh kesef functions as כסף. kesef.
Okay, same idea. ואי דלית בהו שווה פרוטה, ve-ee deleit behu shaveh
perutah, מאי איריא תבואה וכלים? mai irya tivuah ve-kelim? So now he
says, okay, so we know that we're not excluding things that are
of value. We know we have a principle of שווה כסף shaveh
kesef here and nevertheless we're excluding תבואה וכלים, tivuah ve-kelim, food and
vessels. Now why? If it's that they're not worth a פרוטה, perutah,
so then it's not because they're vessels or you know or grain.
מאי איריא תבואה וכלים אפילו כסף נמי? mai irya tivuah ve-kelim afilu
kesef nami? Even if it was real money, it's a different point.
It's just to exclude stuff less than a פרוטה. perutah. Okay, it
seems that there's something specific about these items even though they're worth
a פרוטה. perutah. אלא
לאו דאית בהו שווה פרוטה? ela lav de-it behu shaveh perutah? Must
be that it has a שווה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. וכיון דלא קייצי
להו, ve-keivan delo kaitzi lehu, and nevertheless since their values are indeterminate,
right, so therefore it does not, you know, they don't, they don't
work. And therefore do you see that we can only use things
that have determined values. Now of course, you know, if that's true
that would exclude most שווה כסף, shaveh kesef, unless things, you know,
that have, you know, I mean, how would you say when something
has a determined value? I mean, one sells for this much, another
sells it for that much, what exactly does that mean? How indeterminate
does it have to be? What if somebody assigns a value to
it? Okay, so we'll see about all of that. But he certainly
says you see that we cannot just assume anything of value works.
There is this principle of קייץ. kaitz. So let's see what the
response back is. ואידך הכי קאמר, ve-idach hachi ka-amar, and how would
רבא Rava respond back? הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar, no here's how, here's
the point. בתורת כסף הוא נקנה ואינו נקנה בתורת תבואה וכלים. betorat
kesef hu niknah ve-eino niknah betorat tivuah ve-kelim. When you purchase an
עבד עברי, eved ivri, it has to be giving something that is
functioning as money. So it has to be by paying for him,
okay, בתורת כסף, betorat kesef, and not something that is a type
of a חליפין. chalipin. Now חליפין chalipin of course could exactly be
seen, if you think about it in a certain way, it could
be seen as barter exchange and that's exactly שווה כסף, shaveh kesef,
something that's functioning as כסף kesef and that's what a barter is.
But that's not the general point here about חליפין. chalipin. חליפין chalipin
here is generally understood more like the handkerchief type of a חליפין
chalipin that you take something that is a, now normally it's a
כלי, kli, a vessel, and the principle is it doesn't even have
to have a שווה פרוטה, shaveh perutah, but it is some object
of significance, it's not about its value, you know, or it's not
about its cost, right? The difference between what's a, what's, they say
a cynic is? Somebody who knows the cost of everything and the
value of nothing. So anyway, a כלי kli even like a sewing
needle is less than a פרוטה, perutah, the cost, but it's something
of value, it has, it has a function. So you take something
of value and you know like hand over the glove, שלף איש
נעלו, shalaf ish naalo, and you go ahead or your shoe, and
you take it and that signifies commitment and finalizing the sale and
that effects the transaction. That's what חליפין chalipin is. So he says,
when we're excluding תבואה וכלים, tivuah ve-kelim, we mean don't do it
as an act of חליפין, chalipin, do it as an act of
paying and purchasing and not as an act of חליפין. chalipin. Okay,
but you can use תבואה וכלים tivuah ve-kelim as long as you're
using them for their, you know, you know, for their cost, you're
using them, you know, for what they, for what they're worth, for
their שווה כסף. shaveh kesef. So ואידך הכי קאמר, ve-idach hachi ka-amar,
בתורת כסף הוא נקנה ואינו נקנה בתורת תבואה וכלים, betorat kesef hu
niknah ve-eino niknah betorat tivuah ve-kelim, ומאי ניהו חליפין? u-mai nihu chalipin?
So that's really just excluding framing the act as an act of
חליפין. chalipin. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says, but one minute, okay, I
would understand if you would have excluded כלים. kelim. כלים kelim is
a paradigmatic thing you use for חליפין. chalipin. But תבואה, tivuah, grain,
that's actually a matter of debate. ורב נחמן דאמר פירות לא עבדי
חליפין, ve-Rav Nachman damar peirot lo avdi chalipin, רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says that you can't use foodstuffs to do חליפין. chalipin. מאי איכא
למימר? mai ika lemeimar? That can't be the way you read that
ברייתא braita because תבואה tivuah is certainly not representative of חליפין. chalipin.
אלא לעולם דלית בהו שווה פרוטה. ela le-olam deleit behu shaveh perutah.
Fine, says רבא, Rava, I will say that the case is that
they don't have a
שווה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. ודקאמרת מאי איריא תבואה וכלים אפילו כסף נמי
לא? ve-dikamrat mai irya tivuah ve-kelim afilu kesef nami lo? So then
really why are we excluding תבואה וכלים? tivuah ve-kelim? You should just
say you can only purchase an עבד עברי eved ivri with כסף
kesef or שווה כסף shaveh kesef and it has to be a
שווה פרוטה, shaveh perutah, okay? So what's the particular issues of תבואה
וכלים? tivuah ve-kelim? לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka-amar. Goes without saying,
says the גמרא. Gemara. לא מיבעיא כסף דאי אית ביה שווה פרוטה
אין אי לא לא. lo mibaya כסף דאי אית ביה שווה פרוטה
אין אי לא לא. Certainly if you're using money, anything less than
a פרוטה, perutah, think like less than a penny, that doesn't count.
count as money. Okay, and then you're totally using it in terms
of, you know, its its purchasing power and anything less than that
has no purchasing power.
Okay. אבל תבואה וכלים, aval t'vu'ah ve-kelim, but when you come to
grain and a vessel, so you know, I don't know, let's say
it's a pea. Let's say it's, you know, you know, a little
slice of a carrot. It's a- it's- it's- a sewing needle. So
אימא, eima, I would say מדי דמקרבא הנאתייהו, mide-mikarva hana'asaihu, since the
the pleasure is close, meaning, it's not that you use it to
buy something else. The whole idea of תבואה וכלים, t'vu'ah ve-kelim, the
reason it's שוה כסף shaveh kessef and not כסף kessef is that
this is the consumable or this is the object you are directly
using. So since it is the object that you are directly using,
גמר ומקני נפשיה, gamar u-makni nafshei, so the person would agree to
sell himself in a case of an עבד עברי, eved Ivri, meaning
that would be sufficient for the transaction. קא משמע לן Kamashma-lan that
it doesn't work. Now actually, if you think about it, this is
beautiful according to רבא. Rava. Because רב יוסף Rav Yosef says that
I only understand שוה כסף shaveh kessef to function like כסף. kessef.
And in the end, the reason the transaction works is because this
thing is actually something that is an object used to purchase things.
That's the concept of כסף, kessef, right? It's something that is used
that everybody knows its value and it could be used to purchase
other things. So if you're going to give me something that's not
קייץ kayetz like תבואה וכלים, t'vu'ah ve-kelim, that doesn't satisfy being seen
of as a type of כסף. kessef. Unless you make it קייץ,
kayetz, okay? And however you make it קייץ, kayetz, however you set
its value. Then I can see it as a type of a
כסף, kessef, as a type of a thing that you use to
purchase other things. But רבא Rava doesn't agree to the idea of
קייץ kayetz and presumably it's because he rejects the idea of שוה
כסף ככסף. shaveh kessef k'kessef. He rejects the idea that it has
to function as if it were money. For him, when we include
שוה כסף, shaveh kessef, presumably what we're saying is that the purchase
can occur by any object of value. It doesn't have to be
functioning as money. By giving an object of value, that allows you
to be קונה koneh עבד עברי. eved Ivri. That effects a קידושין.
kiddushin. Fundamentally it starts with the idea that it's an object of
value. If that's true, you understand that if it's a coin less
than a penny, if it's a half a penny or something, that's
not considered an object of value, right? Because you think of it
in terms of its purchasing power and its purchasing power is trivial.
But if you think about תבואה t'vu'ah and כלים, kelim, are those
an object of value? There are other scales you could measure that
on beyond the question of how much does it cost. I can
eat it, I can sew with it. So there's a reasonable reason
to think that that might actually work. קא משמע לן Kamashma-lan no.
In the end of the day, since it is learned from כסף,
kessef, even when it's another object of value, the value has to
mean it has to have monetary value, minimum monetary value. Okay, so
that's why רבא Rava says that's being excluded but I had a
reasonable reason to think that that could function. So now we have
still this debate between רבא Rava and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. What
we don't know for רב יוסף Rav Yosef is, you know, what
does it mean to have a fixed value-
קייץ. kayetz. How would you do that? I mean now, right now
we marry with a ring, right? How do we- what does that
mean that it has a fixed value? Okay, so let's take a
look. Maybe it does mean that there's a standard value and you
just go to any store and they'll all agree that it has
the same value. Does it really have to be that like universal
and standardized? So let's keep on reading. Okay, קא משמע לן. kamashma-lan.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, מנא אמינא
לה,
mina lina
lo,
let me tell you another source I have for my position. דתניא
Detanya we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: עגל זה לפדיון בני, egel
zeh l'pidyon bni, טלית זה לפדיון בני. tali zeh l'pidyon bni.
Somebody goes to a כהן Kohen and, you know, you have doing
פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, five שקלים, shekels, and says I'm going to
give you this עגל, egel, you know, to for my son's pidyon
or this טלית tallis for my son's pidyon. לא אמר כלום, Lo
amar klum, then it doesn't count. עגל זה בחמשה סלעים לפדיון בני,
Egel zeh b'chamisha s'la'im l'pidyon bni, now if he says I'm going
to give you this calf valued at five- at five סלע sela
for my son's pidyon, טלית זה בחמשה סלעים לפדיון בני, tali zeh
b'chamisha s'la'im l'pidyon bni, or this טלית tallis for five- for five
סלעים. s'la'im. In that case, בנו פדוי, b'no paduy, it works. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says האי פדיון היכי דמי? hai pidyon
heichi dami? In what case are we dealing with? Because the only
difference between the two cases is what the person said. It didn't
say if it's worth five סלע sela it works. It says if
he said. So we're talking about what are we going to assume
is the actual value of the טלית tallis in these cases? So
the גמרא Gemara says האי פדיון היכי דמי? hai pidyon heichi dami?
What's the case? אילימא דלא שוי, Ileima d'lo shavi, if we're dealing
with an object that isn't worth five סלע sela and that's in-
and that's true in both cases, so כל כמיניה? ko k'minei? Is
he at all- does he at all believe- meaning does he have
the capacity to now magically make it worth five סלע sela just
because he said it? No. So obviously that's not the case because
then it wouldn't work in the second example. אלא לאו, Ella lav,
it must be אף על גב דשוי, af al gav d'shavi, no,
in both cases it is worth five סלע. sela. And nevertheless, it
worked in case- it does not work in case one when he
doesn't state a value. And it does work in case
two. Okay? וכיון דלא קייץ לא. ve-keivan de-lo kayatz lo. But since
in case one it was not a fixed amount, it does not
work. Now here, this is extremely important because this seems to say
that what we mean by a fixed amount does not mean standardized
and that like, you know, anybody would determine that this is what
it was worth, that's not what's being said there. What's being said
is that he actually fixes the amount, okay, and he says I
want you to know that this is worth five סלע sela we're
setting this that is what the value of this object is and
then that suffices and presumably it is worth five סלע. sela. But
the גמרא Gemara nowhere makes some statement that there is some objective
fixed value and so on, right, which would mean that if you
like go back to the idea before about תבואה tevuah and כלים,
kelim, if you say, you know, I don't know, this table, this
chair, this pen worth X amount that that actually would, you know,
which is worth X amount, that would constitute קייץ kayatz that you
would not really need a
שומא, shuma, the language before was שומא shuma like an official assessment
of it. This is sounding that it's not really so much an
official assessment, just asserting the value, that would suffice. Anyway, that's what
would constitute for רב יוסף Rav Yosef and then it genuinely was
worth that amount or at least that amount. Okay, that's what works
for רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, that's for רב יוסף Rav Yosef constitutes
קייץ. kayatz. But without stating an amount then that can't work as
כסף. kesef. Okay, so how would רבא Rava respond? לא lo says
רבא, Rava, רבא Rava said no that's not the case. לא לעולם
דלא שווי, lo le-olam de-lo shavi,
it's not worth five סלע. sela. וכגון דקביל ליה כהן עילויה, ve-khigon
de-kabel lei kohen iluyei,
but the כהן kohen was willing to say, I accept it for
me, you know, I would be willing to pay five סלע sela
for this. So to me, you know, what's it worth, what's the
going rate, what does it sell for, what's the going rate, well
who's buying it, you know, different people are willing to pay different
amounts and therefore that's the חידוש. chiddush. So you're trying to give
him something worth less than five סלע, sela, that doesn't work. But
if you say I'm going to give you this and we're going
to set the value at five סלע sela and the כהן kohen
says that sounds good to me, I would be willing to pay
five סלע sela for that, I consider that to be that, then
that does work. Okay, so that's for רבא. Rava. כי הא דרב
כהנא ke-ha de-Rav Kahana like רב כהנא Rav Kahana שקל סודרא מבי
פדיון הבן, shakal sudra mi-bei pidyon haben,
he took, he was a כהן kohen or actually תוספות Tosafot interesting
תוספות Tosafot which we'll get to in a minute, he תוספות Tosafot
says he wasn't a כהן kohen but he was married to a
daughter of a כהן kohen and that's very interesting, seems that a
daughter of a כהן kohen can accept money for the פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben. Okay anyway and he said אמר ליה לדידי חזי לי
חמש סלע, amar lei ledidi chazi li chamesh sela,
for me I know that this thing normally goes for less in
the market or whatever, but for me it's worth five סלע sela
to me and therefore that counted as a good פדיון הבן. pidyon
haben. אמר מר
בר רב אשי amar Mar bar Rav Ashi now just as a
sort of side note on this, לא אמרן אלא כגון רב כהנא
דגברא רבה הוא. lo amran ela kegon Rav Kahana de-gavra raba hu.
Where that idea that somebody could say for me this is what
it's worth, it's only when that's a reasonable claim. You know if
I said I'm going to give you this Bic pen that I
found on the floor and you say oh for me that's worth
five סלע, sela, like no, you know that's a principle in הלכה
halakhah called like בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם, batla daato etzel kol
adam, like that's not even, you know, that's not a reasonable point,
like nobody recognizes that that's a normal type of a
thing, that
that's a type of a way to assign the value, a subjective
value, that's just you're asserting that, that's not really true, okay. So
for a normal person to say that that would be worth five
סלע sela would be absurd and we could not say that it
counts as if it were five סלע sela for this הלכה. halakhah.
לא אמרן אלא כגון
רב כהנא דגברא רבה הוא, lo amran ela kegon Rav Kahana de-gavra
raba hu, but רב כהנא Rav Kahana he's an important man ומיבעי
סודרא ארישא u-miba'ei sudra a-reisha and you know and it would not
be considered respectable for him to be walking around
without a handkerchief on his head, without some type of a head
covering and therefore you can understand circumstances where he would actually be
willing to pay, he didn't have one, he needed one or something
or you know maybe I don't know this matches my suit and
it's hard to find a good tie that matches my suit, okay.
You could understand circumstances where yes you genuinely would be willing to
pay that much. אבל כולי עלמא לא, aval kulei alma lo, but
a normal person who had no pressing need for it and he
just asserted that it was worth five סלע sela that would not
count for פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. כי הא דמר בר רב אשי
ke-hai de-Mar bar Rav Ashi another case for מר בר רב אשי
Mar bar Rav Ashi זבן סודרא מאימיה דרבה מקובי, zavan sudra mei-imei
de-Rabba mi-Kubi, he bought a handkerchief from the mother of רבה מקובי
Rabba of Kubi שווי עשרה בתלתא עשר shavi asara bi-tlata asar and
it was worth only ten and he was willing to pay thirteen
because you know again it was a nice one, it was appropriate
for his status. So what does it mean, you know, it's worth
ten, you know worth ten if you could find it, if you
can't find it and if this person is in eager need of
it then for him it's worth thirteen. So there's something about a
subjective value that makes sense and then there's just you're asserting that's
what it's worth but nobody really believes you, you know no normal
person. under your circumstances would pay that amount for it. So now
what you have though, again, is a very
interesting
way of reading this ברייתא Beraita between רבא Raba and רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. It's not just about dealing with the evidence and dismissing
the evidence, it's consistent with their positions. רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, who
requires something function as money, therefore a value has to be fixed,
that's what he's saying, קייץ. kayatz. Again, does it have to be
fixed by an assessor, can it just be asserted, does there have
to be a standardized value? That's left a little vague, but a
value has to be fixed. And רבא Raba says, no actually, שוה
כסף shaveh kessef functions not because it's quasi-money, but because it is
an object of
value on its own terms and therefore,
even though as money this handkerchief would not function as five סלע,
sela, because to function as that means that there is
an objective communal recognition of its value as that amount. Nevertheless, if
we're functioning about value, then we could say on a subjective level
for this כהן kohen that is what it is worth, specifically because
it doesn't have to fit into a box of functioning like money.
Okay, so that is a really interesting debate and the גמרא Gemara
does not tell us how we conclude until we get to tomorrow's
דף. daf. And I'm going to cheat a little bit and have
us jump a little bit to the תוספות. Tosafos. If you turn
the page and look at ח עמוד א, chet amud aleph, just
read the line from the גמרא Gemara that's quoted in תוספות, Tosafos,
the תוספות והלכתא, Tosafos vehilchesa, the third תוספות, Tosafos, a long one,
whatever, the one that runs the height of the page. תוספות Tosafos
says והלכתא שיראי לא צריכי שומא. vehilchesa shirai lo tzrichi shuma. He
quotes the גמרא Gemara saying שיראים shiraim do not need to be
assessed and so we פוסקין pasken like רבא. Raba. Okay, great. And
תוספות Tosafos has a whole question, רבא Raba and רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, we always go like רבא, Raba, why does the גמרא Gemara
explicitly have to say we go like רבא? Raba? And then of
course the question is which version of the debate, the first version
or the second version? Is it only when you say it's a
value and then you need an official assessment because the woman might
not be confident? Or is it when no value is asserted and
even then we reject this idea that שוה כסף ככסף, shaveh kessef
k'kessef, very important conceptual question,
and שוה כסף shaveh kessef functions on its own terms and it
does not have to be given any fixed value. So that's the
discussion in תוספות Tosafos and I just want to draw your attention
to the תוספות Tosafos about 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8, if you see ואומר רבינו תם, ve'omer rabbeinu tam, it's sort
of a little bit across from where the תוספות והזקן Tosafos v'hazaken
starts. And he says, ואומר רבינו תם דאתא לאשמועינן דדווקא שיראי הוא
דלא צריכי שומא, ve'omer rabbeinu tam de'ata lashmi'inan de'davka shirai hu de'lo
tzrichi shuma, that the גמרא Gemara is saying by שיראי, shirai, that's
when you don't have to assess their
value, לפי ששומתן ידועה קצת, lefi she'shumasan yadu'a ketzat, because
people could have a range, is it worth 50 or 60 or
40, you can roughly assess the value. ואינו כדי לטעות בו כל
כך, ve'eino k'dei litos bo kol kach, and there's not wide variance
in what people might think it's worth. אלא שאר דברים כגון אבנים
טובות ומרגליות, ela shar devarim kegon avanim tovos u'margaliyos, but other things
like precious stones and pearls, שישנם טובים אל המעט רגילים לטעות בו
הרבה יותר משוויים, she'yeshanam tovos el hame'at regilin litos bo harbeh yoter
mi'shivyom, people can make huge mistakes by a diamond if you don't
know what you're doing. First of all you gotta know is it
a real diamond, but second of
all is it worth $1,000 or $20,000?
The four Cs, whatever it is, you have to be a real
expert. In that case, צריך שומא משום דלא סמכא דעתה. tzarich shuma
mishum de'lo samcha da'ata. They need to be assessed because the woman
is not סמכא דעתה, samcha da'ata, she might think it's worth grossly
more than it actually is worth. Now this seems to be focusing
on the first debate of רבא Raba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef
about סמכא דעתה samcha da'ata and saying that we don't have to
anytime because if you think about it, somebody gives a ring, they
don't say, oh here I'm giving you a ring, it's worth x
amount. We don't have to be קייץ kayatz in normal types of
cases. Again, maybe רב יוסף Rav Yosef would say something that's totally
determined by its weight and everybody would know it or you don't
have to say it, it's only when there's an ambiguity and so
on. But nevertheless,
the second version of the debate, you don't have to be קייץ,
kayatz, but there is a concern of whether this issue about whether
סמכא דעתה. samcha da'ata. And then תוספות Tosafos says it seems a
little bit that this explanation, you do understand it, if there could
be huge variance, there could be an issue of
סמכא דעתה, samcha da'ata, so it's a valuable point on its own
terms that רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam is making, that there's a difference
between silk and diamonds. But also this helps explain a well-accepted practice.
תוספות Tosafos says לפיכך נהגו עולם לקדש בטבעת שאין בה אבן. lefikach
nahagu olam lekadesh betaba'at she'ein bah even. And that's why we have
a practice to get married with a ring that does not have
a precious
stone because if it had a precious stone, even if the guy
would say, hey, this is
worth $5,000, she might not feel confident that it's worth $5,000. Maybe
it's worth less. How do I know it's really worth that much,
you know? Diamonds have a huge variance. So therefore we do it
by something simple ring, it's gold, gold is totally by weight, there's
nothing you can make a mistake. She might not know the exact
value, but you don't need קייץ, kayitz, but there's not a concern
about סמכא דעתא. smichat da'at. I should also say, sometimes I get
these questions about what if the ring is not circle, it's square,
it's artistic, it's this, it's that. And the basic answer is, look,
if it's something that you can go onto Amazon, you bought it
off of Amazon, it's okay, it's nice, it's a little different, it's
a little artistic, they've got a little design, but it's not something
that affects its value. At the end of the day, it's got
a standard value, anybody could go on Amazon and determine it or
whatever,
or just because it's square rather than circle
or it's a...
just because it's a square rather than a circle, those things don't
create a big indeterminacy about its value. If you had a ring
that was made by Picasso, okay, that would be a different story.
Anyway, but that's also why under the חופה, chuppah, the rabbi says
to the עדים, eidim, you see it's worth a פרוטה. perutah. He
says to the חתן, chosson, is it worth a פרוטה? perutah? And
part of the reason for that is because it's also sort of
to address this issue about סמכא דעתא. smichat da'at. It's a way
of saying, like, we're not promising that it's worth anything more than
a פרוטה. perutah. I'm not promising it's worth anything more than a
פרוטה, perutah, so there should not be this concern about סמכא דעתא.
smichat da'at. But it also very much seems that this idea of
קייץ kayitz is not an issue. We continue now on ח עמוד
א chet amud aleph two dots. אמר רבי אלעזר התקדשי לי במנה
ונתן לה דינר הרי זו מקודשת וישלים. Amar Rabbi Elazar: Hitkadshi li
bemane v'natan lah dinar, harei zu mekudeshet veyashlim.
Somebody says to a woman, marry me with a מנה, maneh, with
a hundred, and he gave her a דינר, dinar, and he started
giving her the מנה, maneh, so like example guy said, marry me
with a hundred dollars and he gave her a one dollar bill.
So it works, and then he'll pay the rest, okay? So now
that's strange, he didn't give her the full amount that he said
the קידושין kiddushin was going to be. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? כיון דאמר לה מנה ויהב לה דינר, Kivon d'amar
lah maneh v'yachav lah dinar, since he said מנה maneh and he
immediately gave her a דינר dinar instead of the מנה, maneh, so
כמאן דאמר לה על מנת דמי.
keman d'amar
lah al m'nat dami. From the context it's clear that he said
that I'm not giving you a מנה, maneh, a hundred, as the
money of קידושין. kiddushin. I will give you a hundred dollars eventually
on the condition, marry me on the condition I give you a
hundred dollars, but the money of the קידושין kiddushin is just this
one דינר dinar that I'm giving you. So that's how we'll interpret
it based on the context that he said a מנה maneh but
he immediately gave a דינר. dinar. All right, so it's like a
תנאי. tnai. ואמר רב הונא אמר רב כל האומר על מנת כאומר
מעכשיו דמי. Ve'amar Rav Huna amar Rav: Kol ha-omer al m'nat, k'omer
me-achshav dami. And it's like he said on the condition, then it's
like right now marry me with this דינר dinar I'm giving you,
but eventually you'll wind up getting a מנה maneh into your bank
account. Okay. מיתיבי. Meitivei.
Now I'll challenge this. התקדשי לי במנה והיה מנה והולך. Hitkadshi li
be-maneh v'hayah maneh v'holech. So a person said, marry me with a
מנה, maneh, a hundred, and he was counting out the money with
singles, one, two, three, four, or with twenties, whatever he was doing.
ורצה אחד מהן לחזור, Veratzah echad me-hen lachzor, and
one of them, either the man or the woman, wanted to change
their
mind, אפילו בדינר אחרון, afilu b'dinar acharon, even when you get to
the last, even you're at ninety-nine but before you get to the
last
one, so they can go back, it did not take place yet.
He said marry me with a hundred, he hasn't given her a
hundred yet, and therefore the קידושין kiddushin has not yet taken place.
So it's not a תנאי, tnai, it's not eventually I'll give you
a hundred dollars. No, the object of the
קידושין kiddushin is the כסף kesef is a hundred. And without that,
the act of קידושין kiddushin hasn't taken place yet. אפילו בדינר אחרון
הרשות בידו, Afilu b'dinar acharon ha-reshut b'yado, then either one has the
permission to say I'm calling it off. So you see that when
you say מנה, maneh, you actually have to give the full amount
that is the כסף kesef of the קידושין. kiddushin. So the גמרא
Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what we're talking about
here, דאמר במנה זו. d'amar be-maneh zu. He says with this hundred.
He's got a stack of dollar bills and he says with this
hundred dollars, okay? And in that case, clearly he has identified the
object of the קידושין kiddushin and therefore you need to give it
all. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, that can't be. הא מדסיפא
במנה זו רישא במנה סתם. Ha mi-d'seifa be-maneh zu, reisha be-maneh stam.
That can't be, because the second case in this ברייתא braita is
a case of this מנה, maneh, which makes it clear that the
first case is he just says a hundred dollars, he just doesn't
say this hundred. What's the second case in the ברייתא? braita? דקתני
סיפא, Dekatani seifa, we taught in the end, אמר לה התקדשי לי
במנה זו. Amar lah hitkadshi li be-maneh zu. He says marry me
with this hundred dollars. ונמצא מנה חסר דינר, V'nimtza maneh chaser dinar,
and then he gives her the stack of hundred dollar bills of
one dollar bills, a hundred one dollar bills, and she counted it
and there were only ninety-nine. או דינר של נחושת, O dinar shel
nechoshet, or one of them was not silver, but it was copper,
okay, can't use our dollar bill example, but okay. Anyway, one of
them was copper rather than silver, so it really wasn't worth a
hundred because it was one of them was a lesser דינר. dinar.
So in that case, אינה מקודשת, einah mekudeshet, it doesn't work. דינר
רע, Dinar ra, if however it was a legitimate dollar... dollar bill,
but it was like, you know, it was in bad condition, as
the גמרא Gemara will say, some storekeepers would reject it, but eventually
you go to a bank or whatever, you know, they'll accept it.
It's still legitimate currency. It's just not everybody's going to be happy
to take it. הרי זו מקודשת ויחליף. Harei zu mekudeshet veyachlif. She's
married because you did give her the hundred. You said it was
a hundred, you gave her the hundred and it was worth a
hundred. But you have a responsibility to, you know, give her a
better dollar bill. Fine. Anyway, what you see is the second case
is when you said this stack of one hundred
dollars. And for the first case is you just said a hundred
dollars and nevertheless, until the full hundred is given, right? What's the
difference between the רישא reisha and the סיפא? seifa? In both cases,
you have to give the full hundred, but when you say this
hundred, then if it was ninety-nine,
you know, even if you gave another dollar, it wouldn't work because
you said this hundred, you claimed it was a hundred and it
wasn't. Whereas in the first case, when you said a hundred dollars,
you give ninety-nine, you know, by the end, and then, you know,
if one of them was bad, you gave a hundred, whatever, one
of them was bad, it wasn't a really, it was a forgery,
whatever it was, fine, then you'll give another. Eventually when you give
a hundred dollars, it will work. But in both cases, you have
to give the full hundred dollars. You said a hundred, so the
money of קידושין kiddushin is a hundred. So you see even in
a case of מנה סתם, maneh stam, we don't treat it as
a תנאי, tnai, we treat it as you have to give the
full hundred dollars. So the גמרא Gemara says, so don't, so that's,
contradicts your position.
לא, Lo, no. רישא וסיפא דאמר במנה זו. Reisha veseifa de'amar bemaneh
zu. I'll claim that both cases is that you said this hundred
dollars. ופירושי קמפרש, Upirushei kamifaresh, and the סיפא seifa is explaining the
רישא. reisha. רצה אחד מהם להחזיר אפילו בדינר אחרון ושיש בידו. Ratza
echad mehem lehachzir afilu bedinar acharon veshesh beyado. When you say this
hundred dollars, then you mean it has to be the full amount
and it has to be this amount, and therefore, one implication of
that is that you can retract until you get to the last
dollar. Okay, ושיש בידו. veshesh beyado. כיצד? Keitzad? כגון דאמר לה במנה
זו. Kegon de'amar lah bemaneh zu.
The case is when you said במנה זו. bemaneh zu. Okay, כגון
דאמר לה במנה זו. Kegon de'amar lah bemaneh zu. והכי נמי מסתברא.
Vehachi nami mistabra. Okay, and by the way, and then it gives
other implications of מנה זו maneh zu where, like you know, something
was actually missing of the hundred, and then it wouldn't work even
if you replaced it. Okay, but fine, but we're claiming both is
מנה זו. maneh zu. מנה סתם, Maneh stam, we treat it as
just a promise eventually to pay. So the גמרא Gemara says והכי
נמי מסתברא. vehachi nami mistabra. By the way, that makes sense. דאי
סלקא דעתך רישא במנה סתם, De'ei salka dachateich reisha bemaneh stam, if
the רישא reisha was a case that you just said a hundred,
not this hundred, השתא במנה סתם לא הוי קידושא במנה זו מיבעיא?
hashta bemaneh stam lo havei kiddusha bemaneh zu mibaya? If you say
just a hundred and it doesn't work until you give the last
dollar, then obviously when you said this hundred, you have to give
the full amount. So why would you even need the second case?
Now there's an obvious answer to that which the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. No, אי משום הא לא איריא. ei mishum ha
lo irya. If that was your question, that's not a good point.
תנא סיפא לגלויי רישא. Tana seifa legiluyei reisha.
You said that the second case to make it clear the first
case, שלא תאמר רישא במנה זו אבל במנה סתם הוי קידושין. shelo
tomar reisha bemaneh zu aval bemaneh stam havei kiddushin. You shouldn't think
that the first case is only when you said מנה זו, maneh
zu, but if you said מנה סתם, maneh stam, you didn't say,
you said a hundred, not this hundred, then it would just be
a promise for a hundred dollars.
So תנא סיפא במנה זו. tana seifa bemaneh zu. It gave you
a case in the end when you said this hundred. מכלל דרישא
במנה סתם, Michlal dereisha bemaneh stam, that the first case is when
you just said a hundred. ואפילו הכי, Ve'afilu hachi, and nevertheless, לא
הוי קידושין, lo havei kiddushin, it doesn't work. And I would clarify
that even further, which is that there's still a difference between the
רישא reisha and the סיפא. seifa. The רישא reisha that says מנה
סתם, maneh stam, it makes clear that, you know, eventually you have
to give a hundred dollars. But if one of the dollars is
bad, you just replace it because you didn't promise any particular hundred
dollars. So yes, that does tell us that when you say a
hundred, you have to give the full hundred. But nevertheless, the סיפא
seifa when it says מנה זו maneh zu is teaching you another
חידוש. chiddush. Maybe we could have figured it out on our own,
but it's still teaching you another חידוש. chiddush. That when you say
not a hundred, but this hundred, then if there was something the
wrong with this hundred, it doesn't work to replace it. You promised
this hundred, so the whole hundred has to be here. That's the
point of the סיפא. seifa. So to some level, maybe we could
have figured it out, but still it is an additional, it's a
new point that's not true about the first case of מנה סתם.
maneh stam. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says we have two
ways of reading this. One way to read it is that the
only problem is מנה זו, maneh zu, but מנה סתם, maneh stam,
you know, we treat it basically as a promise, not as saying
that the full hundred is money of the קידושין. kiddushin. And the
other case is is that, no,
is that,
right, so that both cases would be cases of מנה זו, maneh
zu, but מנה סתם maneh stam would be like we had said.
And the other case seems to contradict the reading, which is the
simpler reading, is that even מנה סתם, maneh stam, you have to
give the full hundred. You could replace a bad one, but you
have to give the full hundred. And that seems to contradict our
claim where we're claiming that it is just a תנאי. tnai. So
let's take a look now. The גמרא Gemara is going to make
another distinction between the two
cases.
You're contorting yourselves, you're making this so difficult, מנה זו, manah zu,
מנה סתם. manah stam. Yes, the ברייתא braita is מנה סתם, manah
stam, and you have to give the full hundred. Okay, but nevertheless,
the reason there we assume when you say I'll give you a
hundred, I'm marrying you with a hundred and we assume that that
means the full hundred is the money of קידושין kiddushin is because
then you start counting out, I'm marrying you with a hundred, one,
two, three, four, five. So it's make that that action makes it
clear that you mean the full hundred is the כסף kesef of
קידושין. kiddushin. When you say I will marry you with a hundred,
here's twenty dollars, and then you walk away, okay, then that action
makes it clear that the hundred is a תנאי tnai and the
twenty dollars is the כסף kesef of קידושין. kiddushin. Sort of leaves
you wondering what happens if there's,
you know, when no action afterwards makes it clear, but anyway, but
in both of these cases the action immediately afterwards clarifies whether the
hundred is the money of the קידושין kiddushin or whether the hundred
is the תנאי tnai and both of them can be cases of
מנה סתם. manah stam. That is clearly the easiest way of reading
it. And then the difference between מנה סתם manah stam and מנה
זו, manah zu, even when מנה סתם manah stam is the full
hundred is the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, is that there if something
is wrong with the hundred you gave you could just give a
different hundred whereas מנה זו, manah zu, you know, you can't exchange
it once that was identified as the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin and
it wasn't what it said it was, there's no קידושין. kiddushin. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: האי דינר של נחושת היכי
דמי? Hai dinar shel nechoshet heichi dami? What's the case of this
דינר של נחושת dinar shel nechoshet when it winds up being copper
and not silver that it's not good? אי דידעה ביה סברה וקיבלה.
I de-yada bah savara ve-kibla. If she knew it that it was
נחושת nechoshet and she knew it wasn't the full hundred, so then
knowingly accepting it, you know, should make it okay. Which is interesting,
he says it's a hundred and it's really ninety-nine, ninety-nine and a
half or whatever it is, but since she's aware of that that
makes it acceptable. Sort of reminds us before of the גמרא Gemara
like by the פדיון הבן, pidyon ha-ben, I'm willing to accept it,
it's not what you said but I'll treat it as if it
were, still a little bit funny, right, because it's not how he
was framing what the act of the קידושין kiddushin was. But the
גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא דיהבני לה בליליא. lo tzricha de-yahavni leh
be-leilya. Okay, she didn't know, it was at night, so she couldn't
look at the coins and see that one of them was copper.
אי נמי דאשתכח ליה ביני זוזי. I nami de-ishtakach leh benei zuzei.
Okay, no, you know, it was a whole big pile of thing
and she didn't see this and then afterwards she was sifting through
it and she saw that one of them was copper. האי דינר
רע היכי דמי? Hai dinar ra heichi dami? Now when it's a
דינר רע, dinar ra, it works, but you should exchange it. Okay,
what's the case? אי דלא נפיק, I de-lo nafik, if it's not,
you know, can't be spent, you know, if it's not acceptable by
the storekeepers, so היינו דינר של נחושת, haynu dinar shel nechoshet, same
point, then it's not usable then it's not a hundred
dollars that can be spent out of the marketplace.
אמר פפא כגון דנפיק על ידי הדחק. Amar Papa kegon de-nafik al
yedei hadach. No, no, no, you know, yes, it's still valid currency,
but not everybody will be happy to accept it. But since it's
still valid currency, that's why it still works. Okay fine. So we've
now the debate of רבא Rava and רב יוסף Rav Yosef about
שומא shuma where we פסקן paskin in the end that she I
don't need שומא shuma and שוה כסף shaveh kesef can function as
value, not necessarily as quasi-כסף, kesef, and this issue about a hundred
and then giving twenty, you know, whether the hundred is considered the
entire כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin or whether it's a תנאי tnai and
the difference between מנה זו manah zu and מנה סתם. manah stam.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, last line. אמר רב אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Amar Rav Nachman, אמר לה התקדשי לי במנה הניח לה משכון
עליה אינה מקודשת. amar lah hitkadshi li be-manah hiniach lah mashkon aleha
einah mekudeshet. A man says to a woman, marry me with a
hundred dollars and here, take my watch as משכון mashkon as collateral.
Okay, she's not married. Okay, I mean unless he gives the hundred,
but she's not married now. Okay. מנה אין כאן משכון אין כאן.
Manah ein kan mashkon ein kan. Since he didn't give her the
hundred, the משכון, mashkon, the watch, doesn't, it's collateral or it's a
way of making it like, you know, it makes us sort of
think about what, for example, like יהודה ותמר, Yehuda ve-Tamar, whatever, you
know, I'm gonna, it's a way of like asserting I'm going to
fulfill my promise, okay, but nevertheless even though he gave her an
object of value that wasn't the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. And since
the and since the מנה manah wasn't there, the משכון, mashkon, I
mean משכון mashkon is there but the משכון mashkon doesn't count as
כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Okay. איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן. Eitibeh Rava le-Rav
Nachman. So רבא Rava asked רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: קידשה במשכון מקודשת.
kiddeshah be-mashkon mekudeshet. There we have a ברייתא braita that teaches that
if a man marries a woman with משכון mashkon she's married. So
the גמרא Gemara says: התם במשכון דאחרים מדרב יצחק. hatam be-mashkon de-acherim
me-d'Rav Yitzchak. No, no, no, that's when the guy who wants to
marry her, ראובן, Reuven, okay ראובן Reuven lent a hundred dollars to
שמעון. Shimon. And now he's holding on to שמעון's Shimon watch as
משכון mashkon as collateral for the loan. And what he does is
he gives שמעון's Shimon watch to the woman. Okay, so did he
give the woman an object of value? Let's take a look. Okay,
so I mean that he owns. So the גמרא Gemara says: Yes,
he has an ownership in שמעון's Shimon watch. דרב יצחק דאמר רב
יצחק. De-Rav Yitzchak d'amar Rav Yitzchak. דאמר רב יצחק, d'amar Rav Yitzchak,
מניין לבעל חוב שקונה משכון, minayin l'ba'al chov she'koneh mashkon, how do
you know that the creditor actually owns the collateral? שנאמר ולך תהיה
צדקה, shene'emar ul'cha tihiyeh tzedakah, when you return the collateral each evening
or each morning, if it's a night garment or a day garment,
the Torah says ולך תהיה צדקה. ul'cha tihiyeh tzedakah. אם אינו קונה,
im eino koneh, if he doesn't own it, צדקה מניין, tzedakah minayin,
why is it considered to be an act of righteousness giving it
back? מכאן לבעל חוב שקונה משכון, mikan l'ba'al chov she'koneh mashkon, so
here you see that he owns this משכון. mashkon. Now, a couple
of important questions here, right? Number one is תוספות Tosafot just says
that this actually is a case, there's a difference between whether you
take the collateral in the case of רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, when
you take it not at the moment of loan as opposed to
when you take the collateral at the moment of loan, but okay,
nevertheless, from one case we can assume that the other case, since
in this case you have an ownership, you have an ownership there
as well. Okay, the other important point is that what do you
mean why is there צדקה? tzedakah? Even if you don't own it,
if you have a right to hold on to it and now
you're giving it back to him, that's an act of righteousness, that's
an act of piety. So take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, צדקה
מניין. tzedakah minayin.
תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר איכא צדקה ממה שיחזיר לו לשכב בו.
v'im tomar ika tzedakah mima she'yachazir lo lishkav bo.
What do you mean? There's an act of righteousness by giving it
back to him to use. ויש לומר דדייק מדכתיב ושכב בשלמתו וברכך.
v'yesh lomar d'dayek mid'ketiv v'shachav b'salmato u'verachecha. He'll lie in his garment
and bless you. ואי לא הוי קני
ליה, v'i lo hava kani lei, if you didn't own it, אם
כן כשמברכו עני הוי ליה ריבית דברים. im ken keshe'mevaracho ani hava
lei ribit devarim. Ah, so if you didn't own it, so getting
a blessing from the עני ani is a ריבית דברים. ribit devarim.
You lent him money and what are you getting in exchange for
your loan? You're getting his thanks and his blessings and so on
and that's a type of ריבית, ribit, now a דרבנן d'rabbanan ריבית,
ribit, we're talking here in the Torah, but okay. But if you
actually owned it and then you gave him something that you owned
and he's giving you the blessing for giving him something that you
owned, then it's not ריבית ribit for the loan. Okay, that's one
explanation. ויש מפרשים, v'yesh mefarshim, and this is really important, this last
line, דלא מקרי צדקה אלא הנותן משלו, d'lo mikri tzedakah ela ha'noten
mishelo, כמו צדק משלך ותן לו, k'mo tzedek mishelcha v'ten lo, צדק
משלך ותן לו, tzedek mishelcha v'ten lo,
that צדקה, tzedakah, now this is not the way that the Torah
means when the Torah says צדקה. tzedakah. צדקה tzedakah in the Torah
means righteousness. But in our terminology, צדקה tzedakah is like money given
to the poor. And then there's an interesting question, when you do
an act of גמילות חסדים, gemilut chasadim, when you give a service,
is that considered צדקה? tzedakah? What everybody else wants to know, what
does that count as צדקה? tzedakah? I always say well for what
הלכה? halacha? Do you mean for the הלכה halacha of like one
of my מצוות mitzvot of if an עני ani sticks out a
hand? Do you mean for the הלכות halachot of
מעשר כספים? ma'aser kesafim? I think in הלכתי halachic terms people want
to say does it count as צדקה? tzedakah? So one way of
reading this גמרא, Gemara, again it's not literal to the פסוקים psukim
because that's not what the word צדקה tzedakah means in the פסוקים,
psukim, but is that the technical word צדקה tzedakah is understood here
to mean you have to give him something that you own. It's
not enough to let's say an act of גמילות חסד gemilut chesed
for example. Anyway, okay, that's an interesting point about where he learns
this out from. More to the point though is an interesting question
here about what is the woman really getting? So great, so ראובן
Reuven has an ownership in this
watch and even what does that ownership mean? It probably means a
degree of responsibility if something happens to the watch. Okay, maybe it
means that when we think about him being able to use the
watch as leverage for his loan, maybe it means a right that
if the loan isn't paid, he'll be able to possess the watch.
So it's an ownership that then can turn into full possession. What
does he give the woman? He gives her something that he owns.
But now what does the woman have? I mean, is she not
allowed to wear the watch? She's not, it's not hers to use.
It is an object of value that transfer now she has value
and now she's in a position to give the watch back. So
like what can she do with it? Does that mean that if
the loan isn't paid, he's giving her the right to collect the
loan? He's actually transferring the loan? It's a lot quite it's very
unclear about that. Maybe it's just enough that something of value that
he owned transferred to her ownership and even if she doesn't really
accrue any benefit from it, who says she needs to get benefit?
She now in possession of something that has value that he owned.
Anyway, that's that. The other of course question is that then when
he says I will marry you with a hundred dollars and here's
my watch,
why isn't that a משכון mashkon that she now has ownership of
that? And the answer is because he never said that I am
going so that's the point of the גמרא Gemara before. Yes, maybe
she does own the watch or has a degree of ownership in
the watch. But that's not the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. And since
that's not the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, therefore the act of קידושין
kiddushin did not take place. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, בני דרב הונא בר אבין זבון ההיא אמתא בפריטי. benei
de'Rav Huna bar Avin zavun hahi amta b'priti.
So the children of רב הונא בר אבין Rav Huna bar Avin
were buying a certain maidservant, a slave woman with פריטי, priti, with
like with פרוטות, prutot, with money. לא הוי בהדייהו, lo hava behadeihu,
they said they'll pay whatever, a hundred dollars, okay, but they didn't
have the cash on them. אותיב נכלא עליה, oteiv nichla aleih, so
they said here hold on to this piece of silver until we
can get the money. לסוף יקר אמתא, lesof yakar amta, then
the her value went up. So the person selling her, this female
slave, wanted to now charge more, he said the sale wasn't final,
you never paid the money. אתו לקמיה דרב אמי, atu lekamei d'Rav
Ami, אמר להו פריטי אין כאן נסכא אין כאן. amarei lehu prutei
ein kan naska ein kan. Just like the case by קידושין. Kiddushin.
Yes, you might have given him something of value, but that was
not given as the purchase money. Okay,
so maybe can he, I mean תוספות Tosafos has an interesting question,
at what stage, this isn't a loan, you don't yet owe the
money yet, right? Because you haven't, the purchase hasn't finalized yet. But
does the holding, so what good does the holding on to this
silver thing do? You know, maybe,
you know, maybe just in terms of normal practice, he won't sell
it to somebody else because I know that you've put down a
down payment, etc. But does that, you know, can you force them
to then pay the hundred and if not you'll collect it from
this נסכא? naska? Because there is no real, that makes sense in
a case of a debt because the money's already owed. But in
here the sale wasn't final. So that's a whole discussion תוספות Tosafos
has. How does the משכון mashkon function in these cases when there's
no debt? But nevertheless, the point that's being made is that it
was not given as the money of קידושין Kiddushin and therefore, excuse
me, as the money of purchase, it was just given as collateral,
and therefore the purchase is not final. Okay, אין
כאן. ein kan. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now, okay, so that's those
cases about, you know, about, so we're all dealing with different ways
in which, you know, issues around the giving of the money, right?
So the שייריים shiyurayim was one question, the giving of a hundred
and it was sort of counted or wasn't given in full, now
the giving of a משכון mashkon and not actual giving of the
money itself. Now we're going to deal less with the question of
like what's the object that was given and more how it was
received. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. התקדשי לי במנה. hiskadshi li bimaneh. Okay,
a man says to a woman, "Marry me with this hundred dollars."
And he gave her the hundred dollars. נטלתה וזרקתה לים netaltahu ve'zarkat'hu
le'yam and she took it and she threw it right and she,
you know, flushed it down the toilet, threw it into the ocean,
או לאור o le'ur or into a fire, או לכל דבר אבוד,
o lechol davar avud, anything that would destroy it. אינה מקודשת. einah
mekudeshet. She's not married, even though she accepted it, that immediate act
is basically saying is not saying is is a rejection of and
saying I do not want to marry you. Okay, so, so the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, הא דדתינהו קמיה הוי קידושין. ha detinyahu kamei
havei kiddushin.
The suggestion is, only if she destroys it is she saying that
I don't want to marry you. Okay, if she just took it
and she, you know, she put it in her hand and the
moment she realized it was in her hand, she threw it down
and she, you know, and she rejected it, right? So it sounds
like that would be קידושין kiddushin because she didn't destroy it. Is
that really true? הא קאמרה ליה שקיל לא בעינא ha ka'amra leh
shakil lo beinah
when she throws it she's basically saying take it back, I don't
want it. Why did she have to destroy it to be implicitly
showing that she's rejecting the offer? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא
מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka'amar. No,
it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא דדתינהו קמיה דלא הוי קידושין, lo
mibaya she'desinehu kamei de'lo havei kiddushin, it goes without saying if she
threw it in front of him that it's not קידושין, kiddushin, אבל
זרקתה לים או לאור, aval zarkat'hu le'yam o le'ur,
but if she threw it into the ocean or into a fire,
אימא כיון דמיחייבא בהו, eima kivan de'michayva behu,
now she actually, if she's not accepting it for קידושין kiddushin money,
so it's his money that she just destroyed, she's going to have
to reimburse him. So since, so if that's true, we have two
ways of reading this, either she's willing to destroy his money in
order to to show how angry she is, and then she's going
to have to pay him a hundred dollars, or she accepted it
and then she just destroyed it to waste her own money. But,
but you know there's a real cost to her interpreting it the
first way, she's going to have to reimburse him a hundred dollars.
So, כיון דמיחייבא בהו קידושי קדשה נפשה, kivan de'michayva behu kiddushei kadshe
nafsheh,
maybe I should say that really she did do the do what
you think she did which would have made her obligated a hundred
dollars, she actually, well, say, agreed to be מקדש. mekadesh. והא דקעבדה
הכי, ve'ha deka'avda hakay, so why did she then throw it into
the fire? סברה אבדקיה להאי גברא אי רתחנא הוא או לא. savra
ebdakia le'hai gavra i ritcha hu o lo. I'm going to,
let me check this guy out to see how good his anger
management is, to see if he's going to get upset or not.
Now, you might want to check him out before the קידושין kiddushin
and not after you've accepted the קידושין. kiddushin. Maybe you'll, maybe it's
like a תנאי, tenai, if he doesn't get angry then I will
have accepted it. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says in that
case there's a, I could have imagined that not to read it
that she's rejecting the offer because then that interpretation will mean she'll
have to reimburse him a hundred dollars. But nevertheless, that is how
I am going to read it. קא משמע לן kamashma lan that
that's not what we said. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Okay, another case
about relating to her acceptance of it. התקדשי לי במנה. hiskadshi li
bimaneh.
He says to her, "Here, take it, marry me with this hundred
dollars." And she says, תנם לאבא ולאביך, tneim l'abba u l'avicha, and
she says, "Go give it to your father or to, you know,
to my father, to your father." אינה מקודשת. einah mekudeshet. That doesn't
work, because we say it means I'm not interested in marrying you.
Yeah, you want to waste your money? Go give it to your
dad, go give it to my dad, I'm not interested in it.
Now however if she says על מנת שיקבלום לי, al menas sheyekablum
li, מקודשת, mekudeshes,
on the condition that they accept it on my behalf, then she
is מקודשת mekudeshes because then essentially they're acting as her שליח. shaliach.
Now if you're paying attention, we'll first see the גמרא. Gemara. תנא
אבא להודיעך כוחא דרישא תנא אביך להודיעך כוחא דסיפא. tanna abba lodia
kocha derisha tanna avicha lodia kocha deseifa. And it says both my
father and your father cause to tell you a חידוש chidush in
the beginning and the end. Right? When it says my father, it's
even though she says give it to my father, we don't read
that as I'm agreeing to marry, we read that as, you know,
go make yourself happy, okay, even though her father would presumably naturally
hold it for her and might give it to her and so
on. And when she says give it to your father on the
condition he accepts it for me, that, you know, even though it's
not her father, it's his father, and maybe even though she says
on the condition, maybe she doesn't totally
is confident that if he gives it to his father, she'll eventually
get it. Nevertheless, since she said on the condition he accept it
for me, it works. Now if you're paying attention, you might ask
why is this when she says give it to, you know, my
father, your father different when she says to somebody, you know, we
learned the other day, you know, give it to, give it to
פלוני, ploni, I'll marry you on the condition that you give a
hundred dollars to פלוני? ploni? And that works מדין ערב, mi-din areiv,
if you remember the גמרא Gemara said. And the obvious difference here
is,
is that in, you know, who initiated it? In this case, he
initiated it and her saying go give it to them is saying
I'm not interested in it. In the other case, she initiated it.
And she is saying I want that, you know, you know, them
to have it and I want and actually and I want them
to have it and I'll be married to you if you give
it to them. So it's much clearer that because that that the
whole thing is happening because she has asked for it to be
done and she is saying that I will obligate myself to you
if you go ahead and do that as opposed to here, he
initiated and she's just saying, you know, go take a long walk
off a short pier. If you take a look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says,
אינה מקודשת ואינה דומה לתן מנה לפלוני ואקדש לך דהתם היא קאמרה
ליה מעיקרא. Eina mekudeshes ve-eina doma leten mana le-ploni ve-ikadesh lach de-hasam
hi ka-amra lei me-ikara. She said it initially, she was the initiator.
אבל כאן משטה היא בו כלומר תן מעותיך להם. Aval kan meshatei
hi bo kelomar ten ma'osecha lahem. Here she's just like mocking him.
Okay. You could also say that the whole idea of ערב, areiv,
by the way, is when this, you know, when when it was
happening because somebody initiated, meaning it's not just a question of her
intent whether she wants it to work or doesn't want it to
work, but also that this principle of ערב areiv was that the
transaction occurred on account of that person. Okay. Anyway, let's see the
next line in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
תנה לפלוני, tna le-ploni, second wide line in the גמרא, Gemara, give
it to
פלוני, ploni, אינה
מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. על מנת שיקבלום לי, al menat she-yekablum li, מקודשת.
mekudeshes. So basically the exact same except instead of אבא ולאביך, abba
u-l'avicha, it says give it to ראובן, Reuven, it doesn't work after
he offers her the money. If she said on the condition that
ראובן Reuven will accept it, it does work. וצריכא, u-tzricha, and you
need that case. אי אשמעינן אבא ולאביך, ee ashmeinan abba u-l'avicha, התם
הוא דכי אמרה על מנת שיקבלום לי הוי קידושין, hasam hu de-chi
amra al menat she-yekablum li havi kiddushin, דסמכא דעתה עלייהו. de-samcha da'atah
aliyei.
Okay, my father, your father, at least we're all in the family,
there when she says on the condition they accept it for me,
we can assume that it works because, you know, she says that
they'll essentially be my שליח shaliach and she trusts that it'll the
money will come to her. דסמכא דעתה עלייהו סברה עבדין לי שליחותי,
de-samcha da'atah aliyei savra avdin li sheluchusai, she assumes
she trusts them and she assumes they'll act as her as her
agents. אבל פלוני, aval ploni, but when just say פלוני, ploni, לא,
lo, even though she says on the condition, she, you know, maybe
she's still just kidding around or whatever, she doesn't really think he's
going to act and maybe if he does act, you know, if
he does accept it, she's not sure she's going to get it.
No, nevertheless, she said on that condition, so we assume that is
like appointing him a שליח shaliach and it does work. אי אשמעינן
פלוני, ee ashmeinan ploni, if you had just said the case of
פלוני, ploni, הכא הוא דכי אמרה תנה לפלוני לא הוי קידושין, hacha
hu de-chi amra tnem le-ploni lo havi kiddushin, that's if you had
just said give it to him, not on the condition he accepts
it, just go give it to ראובן, Reuven, you would say she's
just mocking him, it's not קידושין. kiddushin. דלא מקרבא דעתה לגביה, de-lo
mekarva da'ata legabei,
she doesn't feel close to that to that base, למיהב ליה במתנה,
le-meiselei be-matana,
that, you know, it should that we should read it as go
give it to ראובן Reuven which is, oh, I'd love to be
married to you and you know what you can do? You can
do go give that money to ראובן, Reuven, it'll be like I
accepted it and I'm directing a gift to him. No, we would
never say such a thing. You know, why does she feel so
close to ראובן? Reuven? Obviously she's just mocking him and saying you
want to waste your money, go give it to ראובן. Reuven. אבל
אבא
ואביך, aval abba ve-avicha, but in the case of my father, your
father,
דמקרבא דעתה לגבייהו, de-mekarva da'ata legabeihu, you know, she feels very close
to them, אימא במתנה אביסת ניחא לה, eima be-matana avisa niha lei,
I might think that what she's really saying is, yes, I accept
your offer of קידושין kiddushin and now, you know what? I don't
need the money, so would you mind go giving it to my
father, your father? That's what I'm doing with my כסף של קידושין,
kesef of kiddushin, you know, that you have offered to give me.
But she that it is actually an acceptance. So וצריכא, tzricha, it
has to tell you that that doesn't work. Now, of course,
in... Whoever accepted the כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin for her, does
that, is that going to turn that into a case of that
they should accept it on my behalf? That's not the language of
מתנה. Matana. Maybe that becomes more of a case of the ערב
Areiv of the earlier גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara doesn't fully unpack
that.
Okay, one more case for the end of today. תנו רבנן: Tanu
Rabbanan: התקדשי לי במנה. Hitkadshi li be-maneh. He says marry me with
a מנה. maneh. She says תנהו על גבי סלע, Tnehu al gabei
sela, go put it on a rock. אינה מקודשת. Eina mekudeshet. She's
not married. Obviously, a, it's mocking; b, she never receives it. ואם
היה סלע שלה מקודשת. Ve-im haya sela shela mekudeshet. But if it's
her rock, it does work. Okay, why? So רש"י Rashi says, well,
because then she קונה koneh it with a קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer,
okay, because it's putting it in her property. בעי רב ביבי: Ba'ei
Rav Bibi: So רב ביבי Rav Bibi said, סלע של שניהם מהו?
sela shel sheneihem mahu? תיקו. Teiku. What if it's both of their
rocks? So we're going to leave that unanswered. They both equally own
it. Now תוספות Tosafot says, one minute, but if it was the
issue of חצר, chatzer, we would know the answer. When one partner
is trying to sell to another partner in a field that they
jointly owned, then you can't be קונה. koneh. So if they both
equally own the rock, then it won't work for her as a
חצר. chatzer. So what's the issue? So if you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says,
אם היה סלע שלה מקודשת. im haya sela shela mekudeshet. פירש בקונטרס
דחצר קונה לה. Peresh be-kuntres de-chatzer koneh lah. ולא נהירא, Ve-lo nehira,
that doesn't make sense. ואם כן מאי בעי סלע של שניהם מהו?
פשיטא דאינה קונה כיון דהוא חצר של שניהם. Ve-im ken mai ba'ei
sela shel sheneihem mahu? Peshita de-eina koneh keivan de-hu chatzer shel sheneihem.
Then he quotes the whole גמרא Gemara that proves that. ונראה לפרש,
Ve-nira le-faresh, two lines from the bottom, end of the line.
דהכא התם אין תלוי בקנין חצירה אלא כשהסלע שלה סמכה דעתה, De-hacha
hatam ein talui be-kinyan chatzeirah ela keshe-hasela shela samcha da'atah, then she
trusts that maybe she'll be able to retrieve the money.
ובשאינה שלה לא סמכה דעתה, U-vshe-einah shela lo samcha da'atah, she doesn't
have reliance. ואי כששל שניהם סמכה דעתה או לא. Ve-i keshe-shel sheneihem
samcha da'atah o lo. Now this is of course completely bizarre, because
who the heck cares about סמכה דעתה samcha da'atah or not סמכה
דעתה? samcha da'atah? She never received the money, it never came into
her possession. So you know, we're seeing a lot of weird things,
the גמרא Gemara about ערב Areiv and קונה מדין ערב koneh midin
areiv and קונה מדין עבד עברי, koneh midin eved ivri, and now
we're dealing with that it's a rock but it might not be
a rock that she owns, you know, or maybe if she meant
give it as a gift. All these ways in which we're not
it's not you know clear that it really is about taking possession
of the object.
Similar questions came up in גיטין, Gittin, right, about how much is
it an act of giving or is it about putting it and
taking possession? All right, so that is obviously something that gets discussed.
One last case: התקדשי לי בכיכר, Hitkadshi li be-kikar, marry me with
this loaf of bread. תנהו לכלב, Tnehu le-kelev, give it to the
dog. אינה מקודשת, Eina mekudeshet, doesn't work. ואם היה כלב שלה, Ve-im
haya kelev shela, מקודשת. mekudeshet. But if it's her dog, it does
work, right, because then she's feeding her dog and then it works.
Now, again, does it work because she took possession? Does it work
because she's getting benefit from the fact that he's feeding the dog?
So really the money of קידושין Kiddushin isn't the loaf of bread,
it's the benefit he's giving her by feeding her dog. Again, it's
very interesting that the גמרא Gemara does not fully try to clarify,
you know, what exactly constitutes the act of קידושין. Kiddushin. We have
to try to figure it out through all of these cases and
try to get a more precise definition. Okay, we will pick up
with this tomorrow.